Inventory of the John R. Bruning Collection
Hoover Institution Archives
John R. Bruning collection
1939-2010
2000C119
Hoover Institution Archives
6 oversize boxes, 1 manuscript box (4.5 linear feet), 37,364 digital files (486 GB)
Videorecordings of interviews of American and Japanese World War II pilots and German World War II submarine commanders; veterans' World War II-era photographs and ephemera; CDs of scanned images relating to World War II; photocopies of National Archives records relating to World War II; and digital videorecordings and photographs relating to American military operations in Iraq and Afghanistan.
Bruning, John R., collector
Access
Collection is open for research.
The Hoover Institution Archives only allows access to copies of audiovisual items. To listen to sound recordings or to view videos or films during your visit, please contact the Archives at least two working days before your arrival. We will then advise you of the accessibility of the material you wish to see or hear. Please note that not all audiovisual material is immediately accessible.
Acquisition Information
Acquired by the Hoover Institution Archives in 2000, followed by an increment of digital files in 2011.
Accruals
Materials may have been added to the collection since this finding aid was prepared. To determine if this has occurred, find the collection in Stanford University's online catalog at http://searchworks.stanford.edu/. Materials have been added to the collection if the number of boxes listed in the catalog is larger than the number of boxes listed in this finding aid.
Biographical Note
John Bruning, a military writer and photojournalist, was born in 1968 in Palo Alto, California. He earned a BA in history from the University of Oregon in 1990. He wrote or collaborated on seventeen books published or pending as of 2011, including The Devil's Sandbox, House to House, How to Break a Terrorist, Shadow of the Sword, Crimson Sky, and Jungle Ace.
As part of his research for earlier writing and commercial projects, between 1990 and 2000 Bruning conducted interviews with World War II veterans, including German U-boat commanders and Japanese pilots and airmen. The latter interviews were conducted in 1997 while he was working in a consultant capacity as the company historian for a software company called Dynamix.
Bruning began work on The Devil's Sandbox, which details the 2003-2005 deployment of the 2nd Battalion, 162nd Infantry, Oregon National Guard to Iraq, in 2005. Six months after returning home, the battalion was deployed to North Central New Orleans in the wake of Hurricane Katrina. For a month, the men conducted patrols and searched for survivors and human remains. Bruning deployed with them as a civilian embed, living with them on a concrete walkway in front of the music hall at the New Orleans Baptist Seminary.
Upon returning to Oregon and publishing The Devil's Sandbox, Bruning founded and funded the 973rd Civilians on the Battlefield (973 COB), a nonprofit organization. This group of civilians serves as the Oregon National Guard's (ONG) opposing force during drill weekends and field exercises. In August 2008, Bruning spent a month with Alpha Company 2-162 at Gowen Field, Idaho, during the unit's final field training exercise before its second Iraq deployment.
In June 2010, Bruning was invited to deploy as an embed to Afghanistan with Bravo Company 1-168 Aviation, a Boeing CH-47 Chinook heavy lift unit from Pendleton, Oregon. Another part of the unit belonged to the Washington National Guard at Fort Lewis. The two detachments were merged and sent to Forward Operating Base (FOB) Shank in the summer of 2010 to conduct operations around Logar, Wardak, and Gahzni provinces. Bruning joined them at Fort Hood in July 2010 and was with them until their deployment in early August. On September 5 he joined Bravo 1-168 at FOB Shank. The next day he began flying missions with the unit, which was attached to TF Brawler, 4-3 Aviation, 3rd Combat Aviation Brigade, 3rd Infantry Division. Mixed in with 1-168 were men and women from 5-158 Aviation, "Big Windy," out of Germany. They were at the end of their deployment, and Bruning ultimately left Shank with them in November 2010.
Bruning went to Afghanistan without any affiliation to a news organization, and he was neither under contract nor in the employ of anyone. He intended to spend his time in Afghanistan writing articles about the military men and women for their local newspapers. He wrote seven articles and had five published.
Scope and Content of Collection
The first part of the records in this collection (boxes 1-7) consists of World War II-related materials. The bulk of this part of the collection is videorecordings of interviews with American and Japanese World War II pilots and German World War II submarine commanders conducted between 1990 and 2000. There are a small number of photographs taken during the war that some of the interviewed veterans gave to Bruning, as well as some miscellaneous ephemera. This part of the collection also contains twelve CDs. One holds scanned images from the National Archives, another holds scanned images of a war diary, and the remainder are believed to hold further scanned images, most likely from the National Archives and the collections of veterans Bruning interviewed. Finally, there are some photocopies of National Archives records about Japanese forces at the start of the war, American aviation strategy, and the war diary of a Marine squadron. These materials were collected by Bruning in the course of his work and used for his book projects, as well as articles and other publications.
The videorecordings were arranged into subseries based on the nationality of the interviewees. In the case of the American and Japanese interviews, the tapes were then arranged alphabetically by the subject’s last name. The German tapes, for the most part, were ordered according to the donor’s labels, which were numbered sequentially (except in the case of those which weren’t numbered; those were grouped by interviewee). The photographs, which had no discernible original order, were divided into subseries based on the subject/content of the photo. Some miscellaneous ephemera, which may all be from J.E. Gabrio, was separated from the photographs and placed in its own series. The photocopies of National Archives records were left as originally received.
Most of the still and moving images of National Guard training and deployment in New Orleans after Hurricane Katrina (2005), in Iraq (2004-2005), and in Afghanistan (2010), supplemented by a few items dated as early as 2001, were created by Bruning, although some photographs were given to him. The Iraq and New Orleans material follows the deployment of the 2nd Battalion, 162nd Infantry, Oregon National Guard. It fought in Baghdad, 2nd Najaf, the Sunni Triangle, and Fallujah from March 2004 to March 2005. Bruning wrote a book about this deployment, The Devil's Sandbox. After Hurricane Katrina the battalion was deployed to North Central New Orleans; selected photographs from this period are available. The Afghanistan images follow the deployment of Bravo Company 1-168 Aviation, a Boeing CH-47 Chinook heavy lift unit from Pendleton, Oregon. Another part of the unit came from the Washington National Guard at Fort Lewis. The two detachments were merged and sent to FOB Shank in the summer of 2010 to conduct operations around Logar, Wardak, and Gahzni provinces. Bruning's photos follow the unit's deployment in the summer and fall. Additional photographs and videorecordings depict Oregon National Guard training activities circa 2008.
Afghan War, 2001- .; Iraq War, 2003-2011.; Video tapes.; World War, 1939-1945--Aerial operations.; World War, 1939-1945--Naval operations--Submarine.
- World War II Veteran Interview Videorecordings, 1990-2000 (Box 1-6)
  Scope and Contents note
  Videorecordings on 70 VHS videocassettes.
  - American veterans, 1990-2000 (Box 1-2)
    Per donor emails, interviews conducted with American World War II veterans between 1990 and 2000 (though there does appear to be one interview with a German veteran, Walter Goeckel). Titles taken from labels. 26 VHS videocassettes.
    - Angst, Vern -- B-17 gunner, May 3, 2000 (Box-tape 1: 1)
    - Barber, Rex -- P-38 pilot, PTO (Box-tape 1: 2)
    - Clancy, Pat (Box-tape 1: 3)
    - Crosby, Ted -- Navy pilot, PTO (Box-tape 1: 4)
    - Crosby, Verne -- US submariner (Box-tape 1: 5)
    - Croteau, Hugh -- B-25 pilot and POW (Box-tape 1: 6)
    - Davidson, Jim -- B-25 gunner and POW, Italy (Box-tape 1: 7)
    - Goble, George -- B-25 pilot, Pearl Harbor, June 2000 (Box-tape 1: 8-9)
      General note
      Two VHS videocassettes that are both labeled as "George Goble." Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole.
    - Goeckel, Walter -- Herman Goering Div. (Box-tape 1: 10)
    - Heyman, Richard -- P-38 pilot (Box-tape 1: 11)
    - King, Robert -- B-24 gunner, Italian Theater (Box-tape 1: 12)
    - Laird, Diz -- Navy fighter pilot, ETO and PTO (Box-tape 1: 13)
    - May, Richard -- Navy fighter pilot (Box-tape 2: 1)
    - McKeon, Joseph -- Army fighter pilot, Pearl Harbor and PTO (Box-tape 2: 2)
    - McWhorter, "Mac" -- Navy fighter pilot, PTO (Box-tape 2: 3)
    - Moranville, Blake -- Navy F6F pilot, PTO (Box-tape 2: 4)
    - Oliver, Guy -- USMC F4U pilot (Box-tape 2: 5)
    - Reiserer, Russel -- Navy F4F pilot, PTO (Box-tape 2: 6)
    - Runey, William "Bill" A. -- P-40 and 47 pilot (Box-tape 2: 7)
    - Smith, Troy -- P-38 pilot, PTO (Box-tape 2: 8)
    - Thornburg, Bob (Box-tape 2: 9)
    - Van Nada, Jim -- P-39 pilot (Box-tape 2: 10)
    - Voris, Butch -- Navy F4F and F6F pilot, PTO (Box-tape 2: 11)
    - Vraciu, Alex -- Navy fighter pilot, PTO (Box-tape 2: 12)
    - Winthrop, Doc (Box-tape 2: 13)
  - Japanese veterans, 1997 (Box 3-4)
    Interviews with Japanese pilots and airmen conducted in Japan in 1997, in Japanese. Interviewees include veterans of the Pearl Harbor attack, Midway, Guadalcanal and other Pacific campaigns. Titles taken from labels. 22 VHS videocassettes.
    - Abe, Zenji -- VAL pilot (Box-tape 3: 1)
    - Ino, Takashi -- Type 97/Shien/Kamikaze pilot (Box-tape 3: 2)
    - Kimura, Hideo -- Base Service Officer (Box-tape 3: 3)
    - Komanshi, Sadamu -- Zero pilot (Box-tape 3: 4)
    - Konishi, Iwao -- Recon Floatplane pilot (Box-tape 3: 5)
    - Maeda, Takeshi -- KATE pilot (Box-tape 3: 6)
    - Maruo, Hozumi -- Kamikaze pilot trainee (Box-tape 3: 7)
    - Maruyama, Taisuke -- KATE/Type 97/Ginga pilot (Box-tape 3: 8)
    - Matsuda, Saiji -- Army Arty/MP Officer at Rabaul (Box-tape 3: 9)
    - Oguro, Shin-Ichi -- Human Torpedo pilot (Box-tape 3: 10)
    - Okazawa, Soichiro -- Aircraft mechanic (Box-tape 3: 11)
    - Onishi, Sadaaki --Zero-Kan (floatplane) pilot (Box-tape 3: 12)
    - Shiga, Yoshio -- Zero pilot (Box-tape 3: 13)
    - Sugano, Hiroya -- kid, story of Shenga Shrine (Box-tape 4: 1)
    - Takahara, Marekuni -- Ki-97 Emily crewman (Box-tape 4: 2)
    - Takahashi, Kinzo -- Ki-97 Emily pilot (Box-tape 4: 3)
    - Tamura, Heiji -- KATE middle seat (Box-tape 4: 4)
    - Tanaka, Kikuo -- Army Air Unit Service Officer (Box-tape 4: 5)
    - Watanabe, Makio -- Aircraft mechanic/Java Police (Box-tape 4: 6)
    - Yamada, Ryoichi -- Shiden/Shidenkai pilot (Box-tape 4: 7)
    - Yoshida, Jiro -- Pilot trainee (Box-tape 4: 8)
    - Yoshino, Haru -- KATE middle seat (Box-tape 4: 9)
  - German veterans, 1993 (Box 4-6)
    Interviews with some of the top surviving U-boat commanders conducted in Germany in 1993, in German and English. Titles taken from labels. 22 VHS videocassettes.
    - U-boat 995; Kretchmer (1) (Box-tape 4: 10)
    - Kretchmer (2); Hess (Box-tape 4: 11)
    - Kretchmer (Box-tape 4: 12)
    - Gehr Thater; Hess (Box-tape 4: 13)
    - Gehr Thater (Box-tape 4: 14)
    - Hardegan/Thater (Box-tape 5: 1-2)
      Two VHS videocassettes that are both labeled as "Hardegan/Thater." Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole.
    - Thater and Game (Box-tape 5: 3)
      Label on VHS videocassette also notes: "Plus alternate audio version of Kretchmer and Game from tape 11A."
    - Kretchmer (Box-tape 5: 4-7)
      Two VHS videocassettes, noted here as tapes 4-5, that are both labeled as "Kretchmer" (also labeled by the donor as number 5 and 9/10). Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole. There are two more VHS videocassettes, noted here as tapes 6-7, that are also both labeled as "Kretchmer" (but, per the donor, as number 6 and 11/11A). Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole.
    - End of Kretchmer/top sub exterior (Box-tape 5: 8-9)
      Two VHS videocassettes that are both labeled as "End of Kretchmer/top sub exterior." Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole.
    - Hess/sub (Box-tape 5: 10, Box-tape 6: 1)
      Two VHS videocassettes that are both labeled as "Hess/sub." Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole.
    - U955/Van Oesten (Box-tape 6: 2-3)
      Two VHS videocassettes that are both labeled as "U995/Van Oesten." Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole.
    - Westphalen/Grapp (Box-tape 6: 4-5)
      Two VHS videocassettes that are both labeled as "Westphalen/Grapp." Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole.
    - Germany interviews/U995 interior (Box-tape 6: 6-7)
      Two VHS videocassettes that are both labeled as "Germany interviews/U995 interior." Unclear from label if they are duplicates or parts of a whole.
- Miscellaneous Videorecordings, undated (Box 6)
  Videorecordings on three VHS videocassettes.
  - Warbirds B-17, Tape 1, undated (Box-tape 6: 8)
    Donor's label on tape case reads: "Warbirds - B-17, low res., window dub, Tape 1, raw footage." Label on tape itself reads: "Thunderbolt, Window Dub."
  - Warbirds B-17, Tape 2, undated (Box-tape 6: 9)
    Donor's labels on tape case and tape read: "Warbirds - B-17, window dub, Tape 2, 'The Memphis Belle' - 42:00."
  - unlabeled tape, undated (Box-tape 6: 10)
    Donor's note on tape case, written lightly in pencil, reads: "Historical footage spliced in."
- CDs, undated (Box 7)
  Twelve CDs. Ten of them are unlabeled, but are believed to contain photographs. Of the remaining two, one is labeled "National Archives Images - Pacific War, Volume 1," and the other is labeled "UMF 223 War Diary."
- World War II Photographs, 1940s (Box-folder 7: 1-3)
  World War II-era photographs taken by some of the interviewed veterans and given to John Bruning at the time of the interviews.
  - Landscape and architecture, 1940s (Box-folder 7: 1)
  - People, 1940s (Box-folder 7: 2)
  - Vehicles and equipment, 1940s (Box-folder 7: 3)
- Ephemera, 1940s (Box-folder 7: 4)
  Consists of a cut-out article, "'Chute Program Begins For 45-C;" a blank delinquency report with the name J.E. Gabrio at the top; a bill from the King Cotton hotel in Greensboro, North Carolina for J.E. Gabrio; and a map of Paris.
- Photocopies of National Archives Records, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 7: 5-6)
  - Reports re: Japanese forces and American aviation strategy, 1939-1944 (Box-folder 7: 5)
    These photocopies of records from the National Archives include intelligence reports about Japanese forces at the start of America's entry into World War II and American aviation strategy prior to World War II.
  - War diary of Marine Scout Bombing Squadron Two Forty-One, June 1942 (Box-folder 7: 6)
- Digital Photographs and Videorecordings, 2001-2010; 37,364 digital files (486 GB)
  These born-digital, color images depict US National Guard units deployed in Iraq and Afghanistan, as well as in New Orleans in the wake of Hurricane Katrina. In some cases, descriptions of the events and activities depicted were written by Bruning and are included in the digital folder with the images. Several related articles by Bruning are also included.
  The directory structure, folder names, and file names were retained by Hoover almost exactly as received from Bruning. The directory structure consists of folders with descriptive names; it is the basis of the container list below. Some of the digital file names are also descriptive, though many others follow an alphanumeric form generated by the camera, such as SUC50007.jpg. Because the descriptive folder and file names were very long, occasionally exceeding the file system limit of some operating systems, and contained many characters not recommended for file names, Hoover staff slightly altered some of them while retaining their descriptive nature.
  Some folders are noted as being empty. Because Bruning was not able to finish arranging and describing the material, Hoover retained the empty folders in case they provide clues to some of the photographs that lack description. There is also a lot of duplication of images in different subfolders, which may represent Bruning's unfinished work of sorting, arranging, and describing the materials.
  Some of the folder titles seem to suggest that the images within were created by someone other than Bruning. He probably collected copies of some photographs taken by people he met. The photographs in the Devils Sandbox folder were all given to Bruning by soldiers.
  Several types of digital files are in the collection. Photographs are primarily JPG. Many of the JPGs also have a higher-quality CR2 version, but only the JPG versions are available in the reading room. There are also some TIFs, all of which are available in the reading room. Videorecordings are typically short clips available as MOV or AVI files. Bruning's notes and articles are in MS Word files; a PDF file with background information on the Haqqani Network is also included.
  - Devils Sandbox photos, 2003-2005; circa 150 digital files
    These selected photographs taken by soldiers and given to Bruning detail the 2003-2005 deployment of the 2nd Battalion, 162nd Infantry, Oregon National Guard to Iraq. The battalion fought in Baghdad, 2nd Najaf, the Sunni Triangle, and Fallujah from March 2004 to March 2005. They suffered 9 killed in action and about 80 wounded in action out of 700. They were heavily engaged during both Shia uprisings that year as well as the 2nd Battle of Fallujah in November.
  - 41st Infantry Brigade in New Orleans Post-Katrina, 2005; circa 1,600 digital files
    These photographs and videorecordings relate to the 2nd Battalion, 162nd Infantry, Oregon National Guard, which was deployed to North Central New Orleans in the wake of Hurricane Katrina. For a month, the men conducted patrols and searched for survivors and human remains. Bruning deployed with them as a civilian embed, living with them on a concrete walkway in front of the music hall at the New Orleans Baptist Seminary.
    - Operation Southern Comfort
      - Albany Herald
      - B Co photos Sept 7 and 8 my Cam, 7-8 September 2005
      - Bates camera Sept 11 evening patrol met Mimi first time, 11 September 2005
      - Corvallis Times Article
      - Day patrol Indian Village Sept 10 morning and early afternoon B Co 2nd Plt, 10 September 2005
      - FG Times
      - IO article Sept 14, 14 September 2005
      - Lt BAB camera
      - Lt Miller camera patrol with BS Sept 9 morning, 9 September 2005
      - Monday Sept 12 3 Patrols Bravo Co, 12 September 2005
      - Night patrol number 1 Vinnie Dave John Sept 9 2100-2200, 9 September 2005
      - Photos of the historian
      - Sept 8 and 9, 8-9 September 2005
        Folder is empty.
      - Sept 9 patrol escort with Charlie, 9 September 2005
      - Sept 11 2 bus patrols 5 hours 1st Plt SFC Jacques, 11 September 2005
      - Sept 13 night patrol and Dillard Patrol 1st and 2nd PLt, 13 September 2005
      - Sept 15 3 patrols SFC Jacques Tagging, 15 September 2005
      - Sept 15 morning patrol Houston 3rd Plt, 15 September 2005
      - September 18 late photos, 18 September 2005
      - Woodke photos
  - 41st Infantry Brigade Training, 2008-2010; circa 15,800 digital files
    Bruning founded and funded the 973rd Civilians on the Battlefield (973 COB), a nonprofit organization. This group of civilians serves as the Oregon National Guard's (ONG) opposing force during drill weekends and field exercises. They dress as Sunni or Shia or Taliban insurgents, use the appropriate tactics depending on whom they are modeling, and help prepare units for combat and stability/support operations overseas. These training photographs and videorecordings come from field exercises with the 41st or 82nd Brigades, ONG that the 973rd attended. In August 2008, Bruning spent a month with Alpha Company, 2-162 at Gowen Field, Idaho, during the unit's final field training exercise before their second Iraq deployment, and images from this time are also included.
    - 100EOS7D
    - 101CANON
    - 101EOS7D
    - DCIM
    - Gowen field trip, August 2008
      - A Co Aug 11 village attack, 11 August 2008
      - August 12 activities
        - Additional B Co photos iteration 3 Aug 10, 3 August 2008
        - Also rans
        - Aug 12 A Co. village attack, 12 August 2008
        - Medics
        - Rigs and maint
        - Staff photos Aug 8, 8 August 2008
        - Travels with the BC and the TAC
      - August 13 last trip photos, 13 August 2008
      - Idaho trip day 1 and 2, 7-8 August 2008
      - New folder
      - Oregon NG photos July 8 John Bruning, 8 July 2008
        - Promotion ceremony
          - Edited TIF files BG David Enyeart, 8 July 2008
          - Unedited photos BG David Enyeart, 8 July 2008
        - Promotion ceremony Major Welch, 8 July 2008
      - Saturday Aug 9 Gowen Field 08, 9 August 2008
        - Alpha Co
        - Bn TOC and staff
        - Bravo Co
        - Charlie Co
        - Delta Co
        - General
        - Scout Platoon
      - Sunday August 10 B Co village assault Gowen Field, 10 August 2008
    - Guard
      - 100EOS7D
      - A photos
      - B photos
      - C photos
      - Dups
      - Mike
      - Ox
  - Afghanistan, Fall 2010; circa 19,700 digital files
    These photographs and videorecordings document the deployment to Afghanistan of Bravo Company, 1-168 Aviation, a Boeing CH-47 Chinook heavy lift unit from Pendleton, Oregon. Another part of the unit came from the Washington National Guard and stationed at Fort Lewis. The two detachments were merged and sent to FOB Shank in the summer of 2010 to conduct operations around Logar, Wardak, and Gahzni provinces. Bruning joined them at Fort Hood in July of 2010 and was with them until early August, when they deployed. Bruning joined Bravo 1-168 at FOB Shank on 5 September. The next day he began flying missions with the unit, which was attached to TF Brawler, 4-3 Aviation, 3rd Combat Aviation Brigade, 3rd Infantry Division. Mixed in with 1-168 were men and women from 5-158 Aviation, "Big Windy," out of Germany. They were at the end of their deployment and Bruning ultimately left Shank with them in November 2010.
    Bravo 1-168 flew a variety of missions, including Air Mission Requests (AMRs). These routine requests from ground units were for personnel movement or supply/equipment deliveries. They usually involved hopscotching around the province to different FOBs to bring stuff in or pull people out. The unit also conducted air assault missions to insert troops into landing zones and extract them after their missions were complete. It also flew missions to deliver swing sets to local villages as part of the COIN (counter-insurgency) campaign to connect citizens in rural areas to their government in Kabul, carried ballots and election officials to remote villages, and participated in a battalion-level night air assault in the Charkh Valley.